Hello, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. We picked up on כ"ד עמוד א',
Kaf-Daled Amud Aleph, ממש mamesh at the top, and we're in the
middle of a discussion about יש אבילות בשבת, Yesh avelut b'Shabbat, and
the גמרא Gemara had again whether שבת Shabbat counts towards the שבעה,
Shiva, whether that means that there are practices that are going on
during שבת Shabbat that allows it to count or just that the
שבעה Shiva is measured seven days from the outset. To some degree
it might be the issue that's at stake. And according to the
opinion that there's יש אבילות בשבת, Yesh avelut b'Shabbat, the גמרא Gemara
never clarifies how many what range of practices we're talking about, although
the evidence towards that position at the end of yesterday's גמרא Gemara
was a ברייתא Braita that was interpreted to mean that there was
an opinion that there would be a prohibition of sexual relations with
one's spouse during the period of אנינות. aninut. So assuming אנינות aninut
and אבילות avelut have some type of identity
and that that would apply during שבת, Shabbat, that was identified as
evidence that יש אבילות בשבת, Yesh avelut b'Shabbat, although everything else would
not apply. So that certainly seems to be making it pretty clear
that even the side that says יש אבילות בשבת, Yesh avelut b'Shabbat,
the suggestion is not full observance of אבילות, avelut, but at least
some type of private observance and as we're going to see, which
will be on today's דף daf framed as דברים שבצנעא. Devarim she-betzina.
All right, so logically one could have argued that maybe there's full
observance. As I mentioned to you the other day and as it
comes as a shock to many people, but there is one is
allowed to do ניחום אבלים Nichum avelim on שבת Shabbat and we
read the other day the ראש Rosh that speaks about a practice
of a whole entire public ניחום אבלים Nichum avelim after שול shul
on שבת. Shabbat. שבת Shabbat is not about שמחה, simcha, so if
it's not about שמחה simcha and that's why it's not מפסיק, mafsik,
maybe there should be full observance. But again, there are elements of
שבת Shabbat that are against אבילות, avelut, just the sense of it
might not be about שמחה simcha but it's also not about צער
tza'ar and it's
about and it's about at least about pleasure and a sense of
ברכה, bracha, so says the ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. So that's where we are
getting where we are now, the idea that to the degree that
there is אבילות, avelut, we're talking about a private observance of אבילות,
avelut, not a public one. So we're in the middle of that
issue and as we also ended yesterday with a discussion, we saw
a fascinating assumption that practices of אבילות avelut could be inferred from
practices of אנינות, aninut, although in the end the גמרא Gemara rejected
that and that leaves us with a major debate in the ראשונים
Rishonim to what degree the אבילות avelut and אנינות aninut as completely
distinct practices or as some type of a continuum. Okay, but now
we pick up on the top of כ"ד עמוד א' Kaf-Daled Amud
Aleph in the middle of this discussion of יש אבילות בשבת, Yesh
avelut b'Shabbat, again as we've now honed it into issues such as
תשמיש המיטה. Tashmish hamitah. So בעי מיניה רבי יוחנן מן שמואל, Ba'ei
minei Rabbi Yochanan min Shmuel, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan asked שמואל, Shmuel,
יש אבילות
בשבת או אין אבילות בשבת, Yesh avelut b'Shabbat o ein avelut b'Shabbat,
does אבילות avelut is אבילות avelut practiced on שבת Shabbat or not?
אמר ליה אין אבילות בשבת, Amar lei ein avelut b'Shabbat, it's not
practiced. Okay.
יתבו רבנן קמי דרב פפא Yatvu rabbanan kamei d'Rav Papa וקאמרי משמיה
דשמואל, v'kami mishmeih d'Shmuel, אבל ששימש מיטתו בימי אבלו חייב מיתה, Avel
she-shimmesh mitato b'yemei evlo chayav mita, an אבל avel who has sex
during the period of his אבילות avelut is deserving of death. Okay
now, is this at all connected to what we said before? We're
going to see that there's going to be a response back by
רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. Is this just a general statement that he
maybe thought that people were being too lenient with this practice and
he wanted to come out with a strong rhetorical statement against
it or does that mean like even on שבת? Shabbat? Is it
always supposed to read this in the context of the previous debate?
Okay, which would be funny because he just said אין אבילות בשבת.
Ein avelut b'Shabbat. So the גמרא Gemara doesn't really clarify, it makes
an immediate jump from שמואל's Shmuel statement that there's no אבילות בשבת
avelut b'Shabbat to this statement about the consequences of somebody who has
sex during the time of their שבעה. Shiva. So חייב
מיתה. chayav mita. אמר להו רב פפא, Amar lehu Rav Papa, so
רב פפא Rav Papa said back to them, אסור איתמר, Assur itmar,
no no no, שמואל Shmuel did not say it's חייב מיתה, chayav
mita, he said forbidden.
ומשמיה דרבי יוחנן איתמר, Umishmeih d'Rabbi Yochanan itmar, and it wasn't שמואל,
Shmuel, it was רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan who said it. Okay, again
so it's a שמואל Shmuel רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. Now first of
all that's funny, why would רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan need to say
it? Right? תשמיש המיטה Tashmish hamitah has always been in our list
of things that an אבל's avel not allowed to do. So again,
one could imagine that we're talking in the context of שבת. Shabbat.
Okay, but either way so according to that then maybe this is
the issue. The rabbis had a tradition from שמואל Shmuel that it
was אסור assur to have sex on שבת. Shabbat. But we just
heard that שמואל Shmuel said that אבילות avelut is practiced, which I'm
sorry, I said that he said it's not practiced, right? So שמואל
Shmuel said it's not practiced, why is he saying that it's אסור
assur to have sex on שבת? Shabbat? So then the response from
רב פפא Rav Papa back is you got it wrong, it wasn't
שמואל, Shmuel, it was רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
is the one that maybe says that אבילות avelut is practiced and
therefore you can't even have sex on שבת, Shabbat, whereas שמואל Shmuel
presumably would not say it. All right, so again, I'm reading שבת
Shabbat into the whole discussion because otherwise this is completely. sort of
like juxtaposed, irrelevant and obvious point, right? If you don't see שבת
Shabbos as part of what's being discussed, who needs to tell you
that it's אסור asur to have sex when you're in אבלות? aveilus?
We've been saying that all along, right? And why do you need
this rhetoric about how terrible it would be? So it makes a
little more sense as they're discussing the issue of during שבת, Shabbos,
and then it becomes a question of to what degree שמואל Shmuel
really said it because שמואל Shmuel a minute ago said that אבלות
aveilus is not practiced on שבת. Shabbos. Okay, so now we continue.
Okay, איתמר, Itmar, it was... I'm sorry. ואי שמיע לכו משמיה דשמואל,
V'ee shmiah lachoo mishmeih d'Shmuel, and if you heard שמואל Shmuel saying
something, הכי שמיע לכו, hachi shmiah lachoo, this is what you must
have heard him saying. אמר רב תחליפא בר אבימי אמר שמואל: Amar
Rav Tachlifa bar Avimi amar Shmuel: אבל שלא פרע ושלא פירם, avel
shelo para v'shelo peirem, if an אבל avel does not let his
hair grow wild or does not rend his garments, חייב מיתה, chayav
misa, deserving of death, שנאמר: she'neemar: ראשיכם אל תפרעו ובגדיכם לא תפרמו
ולא תמותו. rosheichem al tifrau u'vigdeichem lo tifromu v'lo samusu.
Right, so this is what's said to
אלעזר ואיתמר Elazar v'Isamar after they became אבלים: aveilim: do not let
your hair grow wild and do not rend your garments lest you
die. So therefore, now they are being told not to do what
an אבל... avel... it's very ironic. They're being told not to do
normal practices of אבלות aveilus or else it will lead to death,
and therefore we will read the reverse, that a normal אבל avel
who has to do these things, right? So it's like mutatis mutandis.
They don't do it, a normal אבל avel does do it, and
either way, failure to do what you're supposed to do leads to
ולא תמותו. v'lo samusu. Of course, even besides the reversing of the
practices, it's the problem that in fact here the death has to
do with the fact of their עבודה avodah in the משכן, mishkan,
not just because of lack of practicing of הלכות אבלות hilchos aveilus
or the reverse of הלכות אבלות. hilchos aveilus. But anyway, at least
then you understand what's being said, that it might have nothing to
do with אבלות aveilus on שבת. Shabbos. It's just an exegetical point
made on the verse, right? So okay, fine. He wasn't talking about
sex, he wasn't talking about שבת, Shabbos, he
didn't have to tell someone who had sex...
Well, or they knew there was a debate about דברים שבצינעה devarim
she'b'tzinah on שבת Shabbos and maybe they interpreted it that way. Okay,
so he's saying if you heard something, it wasn't relevant to this
whole discussion. It was about some exegetical point about a verse. Okay,
but on this discussion שמואל Shmuel did not say that, because שמואל
Shmuel again, assuming that the discussion is understood to have been about
שבת, Shabbos, שמואל Shmuel we know says that there's no practice of
אבלות aveilus בשבת, b'Shabbos, so he would not have a problem of
having sex on שבת. Shabbos.
Yes. You're interpreting most of this דברים שבצינעה, devarim she'b'tzinah, and how
does the reverse to have this whole practice that they were מנחם
אבל? menachem avel?
So that sounds... right. So האחר, ha-acher, let me just... I didn't
finish that line,
האחר שלא פרע ושלא פירם חייב מיתה. ha-acher shelo para v'shelo peirem
chayav misa. I'm just starting to finish that thought. So בני אהרן
Bnei Aharon are... you know, won't die if they don't do it.
Other people who don't do it will die. Okay, so if you
don't do it, so again, actually it may be it's a better
דרשה drasha than the one I was reading before. It's that if
you don't do it, you won't die because you know, because you
get a pass, but other people who wouldn't observe it, they will
die. Okay, so that's how it's being read, but that's again funny
because they're being told not just you're not obligated to do it,
they're told you're not allowed to do it. But anyway, that's how
שמואל Shmuel is reading the verse. You, if you choose not to
do the practices of אבלות, aveilus, won't have to deal with the
consequence of death. Other people who don't observe those practices will. Okay,
so it's a fascinating read of the verse, nowhere near פשט, pshat,
okay. Why you need to say that anyway is interesting, but again,
maybe to exhort people about the weight of practices of אבלות aveilus
certainly has some rhetorical point, but not seeming to have to do
anything about שבת Shabbos and we are allowed to sort of say
שמואל Shmuel didn't say you're not allowed to have sex or חייב
מיתה, chayav misa, because maybe שמואל Shmuel actually says that אבלות aveilus
is not at all practiced on שבת. Shabbat.
Yes, it is strange in all cases how he claims like, oh,
that thing that you heard about sex really was about hair. But
in a way there is some like thematic connection, right? Like unkempt
hair like סוטה... sotah... right, and the
rending of the garments of a סוטה... sotah... it's interesting, right? Maybe
there's some association. Yes. Right. Now Michael's point about ניחום אבלים nichum
aveilim is an interesting one, but again, it's you know, and that's
sort of why I've been underscoring it because for in our mindset
it's so crazy to do ניחום אבלים nichum aveilim but you're not
supposed to practice אבלות. aveilus. But the difference is, first of all,
the אבל avel is practicing and the degree that the אבל's avel
practice is like a sort of public demonstration of his or her
like you know, sort of state of of anguish, of misery, of
sadness, of mourning, you know, so that's inappropriate with the theme of
שבת. Shabbos. ניחום אבלים nichum aveilim could be seen as more of
a you know, the אבל avel isn't making any statement about how
he's feeling and it's more of a statement of like concern and
גמילות חסדים gemilus chasadim and you know, and comfort. So those are
not, you know, those are not... it's possible to speak about the
ציבור's tzibbur understanding about how this person must be feeling and the
desire to give, you know, support and comfort, which is not exactly
the אבל's avel public demonstration of that state.
But changing your place is a public demonstration.
Yeah, that's true. That's true. It's a little more
subtle. But that's a good point. Anyway, so now we continue. Okay,
so we don't know, okay, but at least, now, let's take a
look. אמר רבה בר פפא, Amar Rabbah bar Pappa, תנא בבי אבי
רבתי, Tana bevei Avi Rabbasi, which is from אבי רבתי, Avi Rabbasi,
which presumably means like מסכת שמחות, Masechet Semachot, although this is not
in מסכת שמחות, Masechet Semachot, but some collection of ברייתות braisos about
אבילות: aveilus: אבל אסור לשמש מטתו בימי אבלו. Avel asur leshamesh mitato
bimei evlo. An אבל avel is not allowed to have sex during
the time he's in אבל. avel. ומעשה באחד ששימש מטתו בימי אבלו,
U-maaseh be'echad sheshimesh mitato bimei evlo, and there's a story about one
person who did this, ושמטו חזיר את גוייתו, ve-shamtu chazir et geviyato,
and the pigs came and they dragged his גוייתו, geviyato, his body,
you know, sort of through the streets or something. So that's very
graphic.
So, you know, maybe sort of making a statement, this guy's a
pig, and he was, you know, and it was like, he was
too much indulged in his like physical pleasures, you know, very physical,
this whole type of image, גוייתו, geviyato, like his anyway, you know,
his whole body. So again, given this last statement, this seems to
just be general rhetoric around the issue, and maybe it's again something
that people weren't practicing well enough and חז"ל Chazal felt that they
needed to come out with some strong rhetoric. Let's also not forget
that this is talking about the status of sex during שבת Shabbos
because it's an issue of דברים שבצנעא, devarim she-betzina, right? The practices
of אבילות aveilus that are דברים שבצנעא devarim she-betzina are totally, you
know, a person's on the honor system, right? There's no social dimension
to them. So a lot of people, right, will, you know, I
mean, אבילות aveilus is obviously one of the few practices that is
done very, you know, you know, although very, very widely, even among
people that otherwise aren't observant.
And, you know, and certainly in a society that's an observant society,
you know, there's a whole social pressure, people come and they visit
and so on, and there's that whole social, you know, there's whole
public slash social dimension to the observing of אבילות. aveilus. So if
people are compromised on certain practices, it's not at all surprising that
the ones they're compromised on are the ones that have absolutely no
public element to them. And,
and also ones that there's clearly also like a יצר הרע yetzer
hara about. But anyway, certainly ones that don't have a public element
about. So it is possible that this has nothing to do with
שבת Shabbos and is just again a necessary sort of, you know,
sort of recognizing of a problem and of a rhetoric around that.
Okay, yes.
Yes, and maybe there's another idea that having sex is a denial
of the death that just happened, like trying to affirm life.
Oh, that's interesting.
It's not allowed on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. But I think, you
know, if יום כיפור Yom Kippur person might feel, you know, the
desire to like affirm life.
Right,
that's an interesting point. That's an interesting point. Yeah,
yeah, yeah, that's I mean like they sort of say, you know,
that there was like, like right after I mean, extreme comparison, but
right after, you know, the the Holocaust, people were freed from the
extermination camps, you know, that there was a lot of marriages and,
you know, and whatever, that this real need to affirm life. People
were, you know, a lot of a lot of babies were born
soon afterwards. So it's interesting. Okay, אמר שמואל, Amar Shmuel, פח"ז חובה,
pachas chova, now we're going to get back to this issue about
שבת Shabbat where at least an earlier statement was that שמואל Shmuel
said אין אבילות בשבת. Ein aveilus bi-Shabbat. Now we're going to find
that actually שמואל Shmuel at least said יש אבילות בשבת. Yesh aveilus
bi-Shabbat. Let's take a look. אמר שמואל, Amar Shmuel, פח"ז חובה, pachas
chova, observance of פח"ז pachas on שבת Shabbat is an obligation, נט"ר
רשות. neter reshus. What does this mean? So now we're going to
unpack that. פח"ז Pachas is פ, pei, פריעת הראש, priat harosh, you
like letting the, you know, sort of uncovering the hair, not the
hair growing wild, which is one explanation we have of אל תפרע,
al tifra, which is getting your hair not getting a haircut, but
here it means the covering of the head, right? We spoke before
about an אבל avel having to do a whole, you know, wrapping
of the head and of the face. So החזרת קרע לאחוריו, achazar
kera leachorav, turning the rent in the garment behind one's back, not
not sort of, you know, having it in the front where it's
visible. And זקיפת המיטה, zekifat hamita, and
setting the beds straight, meaning that these things you have to do
you have to do the opposite of the אבילות aveilus practices on
שבת. Shabbat. You have to not observe what normally would be the
אבילות aveilus practice in these areas. You have to not have your
whole face veiled. You have to have it exposed. You have to
not have the rent garment in front. You have to have it
behind. You have to not have your bed upturned. You have to
have it right side up. Because all of these things no, what
are you talking about? Every single one of these things is highly
public.
But in your house.
No, מיטה mita is not yeah, that's a good point, but מיטה
mita is not just the bed in the bedroom. Like מיטה mita
is like the couch where people sit and all those types of
things. It's not just the bed in the bedroom. Okay, so all
of these are very visible signs of אבילות aveilus and these things
have to not be done on שבת. Shabbat. Okay, so that's the
אין אבילות בשבת ein aveilus bi-Shabbat point, but now we're going to
see the יש אבילות בשבת yesh aveilus bi-Shabbat in דברים שבצנעא. devarim
she-betzina. נט"ר רשות. Neter reshus. What's נט"ר? neter? נעילת הסנדל, Neilat hasandal,
so, wearing shoes. Now we're going to get back to this issue.
Why is that דברים שבצינא? dvarim she’betzina? You walk outside, people see
you, you know, not wearing shoes, it’s very public. So we’ll see
in a minute, especially if you’re talking about a hot region, that
often people might go barefoot and not wear shoes, especially if, you
know, definition of shoes is like maybe they're wearing some type of
a, you know, some type of a clog or something, but not
real shoes. תשמיש המיטה, tashmish hamita, sex, which is a classic example
of something that’s completely private. And רחיצת ידים ורגלים בחמין, rechitzas yadayim
v’raglayim b’chamin,
washing, and washing your hands, like, and face, you know, with hot
water at night, like you know a type of, like just washing
off the dirt of the day. All those things people don't see
if you've done, you know, if you've basically, you know, if you've
taken a bath or not. Again, goes a little too long they
might smell it, but okay. Anyway, all of those things are considered
to be רשות. reshus. Those are things that are private that by
maintaining those observances of אבלות, aveilus, it is not clear to other
people that you're maintaining those observances. And therefore you are allowed to
do it on שבת. Shabbos. Now, the word רשות reshus is pretty
funny. Allowed? What do you mean allowed to do it on שבת?
Shabbos? So, it's the אבל's aveil discretion. Oh, if you want to
still practice אבלות, aveilus, you're allowed to do the private practices, just
not allowed to do the public ones. So they can decide whether
they want to or not? It sounds like that, which would be
fascinating. Like technically שבת Shabbos over, and I mean, that's it. But
anyway, it's weird to be in that zone. So the ראש Rosh
says, and of course this is a פסק הלכה, psak halacha, and
because it's a רשות, reshus, it's a חובה. chova. Meaning, because שבת
Shabbos doesn't make it forbidden to do these things, then you're obligated
to do these things as a practice of אבלות. aveilus. Okay? So
it's really not חובה chova versus רשות, reshus, it's really like חובה
chova to do and חובה chova to not do or חובה, chova,
you know... so anyway. So you wash your face with hot water,
right. So that's what, so here we get the idea of the
private practices do apply, but now we're going to see what's in
the category of private. We've listed these three. Let's take a look
as the גמרא Gemara continues. So the גמרא Gemara says like this,
ורב אמר, v’Rav amar, and רב Rav says, אף פריעת הראש רשות.
af prias harosh reshus.
Even the question about veiling is discretionary. Again, discretionary meaning, which would
mean that you are not obligated to... let me say it this
way: you don't, we don't say you have to expose your hair
on שבת. Shabbos. A person is allowed and therefore obligated or maybe,
whatever, we'll see, to keep his head veiled. Now that's pretty funny,
veiling of the head, you would think is a pretty public practice
of אבלות. aveilus. So let's take a look. ושמואל מאי שנא נעילת
הסנדל דרשות דלאו כולי עלמא עבידי דסיימי מסאנייהו. u’Shmuel mai shna neilas
hasandal d’reshus d’lav kulei alma avidi d’saymi masanyeihu. שמואל, Shmuel,
why does he say that wearing shoes is discretionary? Again, it is
funny, this point of the ראש Rosh is not in the גמרא,
Gemara, and one does really wonder if the גמרא Gemara imagines this
gray zone of דברים שבצינא dvarim she’betzina being discretionary, that you can
really choose whether or not. Okay, but I'll acknowledge that, but I'll
just read it according to the ראש, Rosh, which is the way
we obviously פסקן, pasken, which is, which is assuming that you have
to do, you know, that you have to do the אבלות aveilus
observance. So why does שמואל Shmuel say you have to do the
אבלות aveilus observance of not wearing shoes? Because it's not obvious. דלאו
כולי עלמא עבידי דסיימי מסאנייהו. d’lav kulei alma avidi d’saymi masanyeihu. Because
very often people don't wear shoes for other reasons, not necessarily because
they're אבלים, aveilim, so it doesn't make it obvious that you're an
אבל. aveil. So פריעת הראש נמי לאו כולי עלמא עבידי דמגלו רישייהו.
prias harosh nami lav kulei alma avidi d’megalu reishaihu.
So uncovering the head, a lot of people also don't necessarily uncover
their head, a lot of people will walk around, you know, with
some type of a veil or head covering and so on. So
keeping your head covered isn't obvious that you're observing אבלות, aveilus, so
therefore why shouldn't you have to do that on שבת? Shabbos? One
minute. So שמואל לטעמיה, Shmuel l’taamei, שמואל Shmuel goes according to his
reasoning, דאמר שמואל כל קרע שאינו בשעת חימום אינו קרע. d’amar Shmuel
kol kera she’eino b’shaas chimum eino kera.
That's a parenthetical statement we'll get back to. Any rending of the
garments that does not come at the time of being heated up,
of being very like emotionally overwrought, you know, that's done more like,
all right, I have to rend my garments, I'll rend my garments,
but you're not doing it with any expression of emotion, that doesn't
count as a rending of the garment. וכל עטיפה שאינה כעטיפת ישמעאלים
אינה עטיפה. v’chol atifa she’eina k’atifas Yishmeilim eina atifa.
And any wrapping of the head that is not like the way
the ישמעאלים, Yishmeilim, you know, the Arabs, wrap their head, that is,
you know, with a much more fuller, complete type of a head,
completely covering the face, then that does not count as a real
עטיפה atifa for practices of אבלות. aveilus. So what would that mean?
מחוי רב נחמן עד גובי דדיקנא, mechavi Rav Nachman ad gubei d’dikna,
until the like edges of the beard, which is basically like until
the cheekbone. So some complete covering, you know, of the, I don't
know of the eyes, but of the nose and of the mouth
all the way down to the cheek. Okay? So that type of
an
עטיפת הראש, atifas harosh, look, you know, is something that nobody would
do unless they were an Arab or unless they were an אבל.
aveil. So therefore if שמואל Shmuel feels that that's what the practice
is, he's obviously going to say you're not allowed to do it
on שבת. Shabbos. If you give the practice as wearing some head
covering over your hair and not veiling your face, so okay, keep
on doing that on שבת, Shabbos, normal people cover their hair for
various reasons. But if it's about veiling your face and having it
come all the way over your nose and your lips and so
on, then that's... really demonstrative and therefore will be forbidden. Okay, by
the way, this whole idea of עטיפת ישמעאלים Atifas Yishmaelim is a
fascinating one, it gets into whole questions about wearing טלית, tallis, you
know, according to some of the גאונים, Geonim, you're not actually biblically
doing the מצוות ציצית mitzvas tzitzis if it's a בגד beged that
you're not wearing, like we say להתעטף בציצית lehitatef bitzitzis when we
put on the טלית גדול, tallis gadol, you know, and according to
some that really would require בגד beged that like really goes like
wraps around the head and wraps around the body and whatever this
עטיפת ישמעאלים Atifas Yishmaelim is. So this comes up in other contexts
as well of what constitutes like a real עטיפה. atifa. Okay, but
that's anyway why that שמואל Shmuel by making it a more demanding
of the practice in general, it becomes much more of clearly a
סימן siman of אבלות, aveilus, and therefore is not allowed to be
done according to him on שבת Shabbos as opposed to רב Rav
that says, you know, maybe it's just something on your head, and
therefore you why not you can do it on שבת Shabbos and
if you can presumably you have to. Yes.
Does this get translated more into like modern פסק? psak? I mean,
shoes are almost always leather. Women's shoes are or can often not
be.
Yeah, so the whole issue about leather shoes and that part of
the definition, yeah, that's I mean, that's a fascinating discussion about that.
Like we, you know, we again, there are some ראשונים Rishonim that
feel that it's that leather isn't the cutoff, the question is how
much is it a real shoe or not a real shoe, and
might change in terms of what that definition is. But again, we
tend to really, you know, פוסק pasken level leather. Although, I will
say that by אבלות, aveilus, again, I don't know, I'd have to
check what people's practices are, but my sense is that while on
like תשעה באב, Tisha B'Av, you know, and יום כיפור, Yom Kippur,
people will wear sneakers, you know, I don't know, my sense is
that at least some people will sort of be more מחמיר machmir
about that by אבלות aveilus because אבלות aveilus also one of the
learnings of not wearing shoes is from a idea- פסוק pasuk about
going barefoot. So, you know, the question is are you saying it's
an איסור issur of נעילת הסנדל, ne'ilas hasandal, which is normally how
it's expressed, or is it a type of a concept even if
not literally barefoot but a type of a concept of barefoot and
therefore that might demand more. Yes.
Is the ראש Rosh פוסק paskening that they have to do these
signs of mourning or they can't do them?
According to the ראש Rosh there's no middle position. You know, either
you have to do it or you have to not do it,
right? Depending on what falls into the דברים שבצנעה dvarim she-betzina category
as opposed to the non-דברים שבצנעה. dvarim she-betzina. The
דברים שבצנעה dvarim she-betzina you have- the phrase is funny, it says
you have to, but it meant you have to do the opposite.
So the language gets confusing. But the basic way it boils down
is, the things that are the non-דברים שבצנעה, dvarim she-betzina, you're not
allowed to do, and the things that are the- you know, you're
not allowed to do the אבלות aveilus form of the practice, so
you're obligated to do the opposite of the אבלות aveilus form. You're
obligated to act in the normal way in those matters. And the
things that are דברים שבצנעה, dvarim she-betzina, the גמרא Gemara says you're
allowed to do the אבלות aveilus practice, but the הלכה halacha is
you're obligated to do the אבלות aveilus practice of the דברים שבצנעה.
dvarim she-betzina. Yes.
Is the ראש Rosh making a stringency or making a clarification?
Well, he says he's making a clarification. He says, you know, and
he's saying what the literal meaning of the text is.
No, he's- well, he's saying that if the text says- he's saying
there's no middle- logically there's no middle ground. So once your text
says it's permitted, what it means is שבת Shabbos doesn't forbid it.
And once שבת Shabbos doesn't forbid it, then the obligation to do
it of אבלות aveilus kicks in. So he's explaining- he's not claiming
he's saying something more, he's saying that's the dynamic that's at work.
Or even if שבת Shabbos isn't standing in the way, what רשות
reshus means is then the obligation- but I'm just saying it's possible
to read the גמרא Gemara more literally, right? That there's actually some
interesting discretion around some of this. Oy, I know that's coming. Yeah?
Is it possible the גמרא Gemara's taking a different position than that?
It's hard- just because of the language of רשות. reshus. You know,
I mean yeah, I agree that that's- no, I agree that that's
certainly the simple sense. I, you know, I don't know, maybe I
could learn too long in ישיבה, yeshiva, so I'm- I'm built to
buy into these readings. It doesn't sound to me to be the
craziest thing ever to say that we mean רשות reshus from the
perspective of שבת, Shabbos, that-
that שבת Shabbos doesn't- excuse me, that שבת Shabbos doesn't forbid it.
Doesn't- doesn't be the craziest thing ever. It feels like the ראש
Rosh's adding another...
It certainly seems that, it certainly seems that. You know, I would
say like this, what- what makes the ראש Rosh even more difficult
is if the גמרא Gemara had said doing these practices is אסור,
assur, שבת Shabbos makes them forbidden, and these things are not אסור,
assur, שבת Shabbos doesn't make it forbidden, then you go, okay, שבת
Shabbos doesn't make it forbidden and therefore the אבלות aveilus makes it
obligatory. You could have at least heard that. But it doesn't say
that. It says doing the opposite you're obligated. So we're not even
talking about שבת Shabbos standing in the way. So I agree, it-
it is definitely a stretch in the גמרא, Gemara, but that's certainly
how we rule, you know. Yes.
But it's not answered in the end of the text, you know,
whose discretion it is.
Right. If it means רשות, reshus, I assume it means each individual
of אבלות.
aveilus. Or you might think, you might think the- right. You might
think that it's the- I mean we just talked about the- ראש
בית דין Rosh Beis Din of a place. You know, it could
be somebody setting a- a standard for a community.
Yeah, the ראש בית דין Rosh Beis Din was a while ago,
you mean by like the נידוי nidui discussions?
No,
we just before-
oh about when he dies. Right, yeah, but- but that's not him,
that's how other people practice the אבלות aveilus for his... anyway, right.
רשות reshus when it means רשות... reshus... Right, but that's not him,
that's how other people practice their אבילות aveilus for him. Anyway, right.
רשות Reshus when it means רשות reshus usually means that the person
it's at their individual discretion, yeah. Okay, by the way, about עטיפת
הראש, atifas ha-rosh, I'll just read you, here's what the שלחן ערוך
Shulchan Aruch says: אבל חייב בעטיפת הראש דהיינו שיחפה Avel chayav ba-atifas
ha-rosh dehinu she-yachpeh ראשו בטלית או בסודר, rosho be-talis o be-sudar, right,
with a
with a cloak or some type of a handkerchief, ויחזיר קצתו על
פיו ועל ראש החוטם. ve-yachzir ktzaso al piv ve-al rosh ha-chotem.
So covering the the top of the nose and the and the
lips. הני מילי שצריך עטיפה בכל יום אבל כשבאו מנחמין אצלו מגלה
ראשו לכבודם. Hani milei she-tzarich atifa be-chol yom aval keshe-bau menachamin etzlo
megaleh rosho lichvodam. Okay, that's when visitors come, he then removes it,
which gets to the fascinating question then how much the פרהסיא parhesia
is. If you anyway, so the רמ"א Rama says, ויש אומרים שאין
נוהגין במדינות אלו בעטיפה וכן המנהג פשוט ואין להחמיר ולשנות במה שלא
נהגו אבותינו. ve-yesh omrim she-ein nohagin be-medinos elu be-atifa ve-chein ha-minhag pashut
ve-ein le-hachmir u-le-shanot be-ma she-lo nahagu avoseinu. Right? So and there's all
these I think there's an earlier place where תוספות Tosafot says that
if we were to do עטיפה atifa it we would be like
a we would just look foolish in the eyes of the גוים
goyim and whatever. Interesting question, it's like so we don't do the
turning up of the bed because that's bizarre, you know, we don't
do you know certain things which were felt at a certain point
like just sort of lost their power and their meaning or almost
became absurd and therefore stopped being practiced. So for the again I
don't know what's you know if there are still Sephardic communities that
do a real עטיפה, atifa, but for the for תוספות Tosafot and
the אשכנזים Ashkenazim they do not. Okay, so anyway, so now let's
continue. Okay, so we have this idea about the public and the
private practices. We're not done with it, but we're going to digress
for a minute to talk about the rending of the garments בשעת
חימום. be-shas chimum. So let's take a look. Oh
I'm sorry, first we have to say another point about this. אמר
רבי יוחנן לא שנו אלא שאין מנעלים ברגליו אבל יש מנעלים ברגליו
מנעליו מוכיח עליו. Amar Rabbi Yochanan lo shanu ela she-ein minalim be-raglav
aval yesh minalim be-raglav minalav mochiach alav. So when is it... Did
I read the...
Did I
skip a line?
אלו בין התיקנו? Elu bein ha-tiknu?
Yes I did. Okay, so we we this idea that you are
a person is not allowed to do an עטיפה atifa according to
according to שמואל Shmuel is only if they're not wearing shoes. But
if they're wearing shoes, right, then the shoes make it clear that
they're not practicing their אבילות, aveilus, so therefore that counteracts the fact
that they're covering their head, okay? Which becomes now very funny. תוספות
Tosafot says: One minute, so you mean that I'm allowed to do
practices of אבילות aveilus as long as I do one thing that's
that that counteracts everything else? Right, so if a person wears the
shoes, then they're allowed to do all the other practices of אבילות
aveilus because the wearing of the shoes makes it obvious that they're
not an אבל? avel? Right? So he sort of doesn't exactly know
what to do with it, and if you just look at the
one line in תוספות Tosafot he says, where is it? לא שנו
אלא שאין מנעלים ברגליו, lo shanu ela she-ein minalim be-raglav, he says:
תימא כהיכי דמנעליו מוכיחים עליו אמאי לא אמרינן אחד מהני מוכיח עליו?
teimah ke-heichi de-minalav mochiach alav amai lo amrinan echad me-hani mochiach alav?
Like there's other things that he does, right, that are not practices
of אבילות, aveilus, like he has the bed turned up on the
right way, right? ונמצא דאינו חובה כי אם אחד, ve-nimtza de-eino chova
ki im echad,
that all you do is you do one practice of you know
you do one thing and and then that'll make and then all
the other practices of אבילות aveilus you can go ahead and do
because one thing shows that the person isn't an אבל. avel. ושמא
במנעלים יש בו הוכחה טפי. ve-shema be-minalim yesh bo hocha-a tfei. Maybe
the shoes is more clear that the person isn't an אבל. avel.
But still the person is. Okay, so so wear the shoes and
all the other practices of אבילות aveilus go ahead and do. So
it's very bizarre that this what's going on in this גמרא. Gemara.
The other thing I will say, and it doesn't get really doesn't
hear an echo in the הלכה. halacha. You don't hear the הלכה:
halacha: what you do this allows you to do this, you do
that, you know there's no type of a thing like you do
all the private all the
private practices and none of the public practices. The other interesting thing
though is is that here we're seeing that an אבל avel is
allowed to do I'm sorry I skipped that...
no wait one minute... yeah we just got through saying that not
wearing shoe wearing shoes is in דברים שבצנעה, devarim she-be-tzina, right, that
wearing shoes is a private thing because not everybody associates being barefoot
with being an אבל, avel, so it's considered to be private. Now
according to the רא"ש, Rosh, that means that an אבל avel is
obligated not to wear shoes, right? And now we're seeing that we're
just saying that if the אבל avel is wearing shoes it has
an impact on covering the head. So that gets back to פשט
pshat of the גמרא, Gemara, right, we just described the possibility that
an אבל avel during שבת Shabbos can choose to wear shoes, okay,
even though we said before that that's in the דברים שבצנעה devarim
she-be-tzina cate- that's in the דברים שבצנעה devarim she-be-tzina
category, right? So again it seems that the רשות reshus really does
mean רשות, reshus, yeah.
But what's the... I'm not really understanding like let's say you decide
not to have anyone over that שבת. Shabbat. So then...
Okay, so part- whether whether there are people seeing it or not
we'll get to, okay? Presumably here we're trying to create definitions of
things that by their nature are are are public and make statements
and make visible the אבילות aveilus as opposed to things that it's
sort of like the idea of like you know what do you
call it of like מראית עין. maris ayin. Doesn't matter if people
are seeing or not, it matters what type of an action it
is, what type of messages this action sends were people to be
observing it.
Like then we'd have to take off the covers of the mirrors
then on שבת Shabbat because that'd be a public
demonstration then.
Well right, right, you're right, that would be the parallel, that's correct.
Okay, so now let's take a look. Okay.
I mean, not everything is like that by the way because the
sex is by very nature private. So, it's a little bit different
than the, it's a little different than the,
I think so. I don't know, that's a good question. I'm not
remembering.
David, when you recently sat שבעה, shiva, do you remember what, did
you know?
All right. Let's take a look. אמר רב יוחנן. Amar Rav Yochanan.
Okay. So anyway, so here we have the list of דברים שבפרהסיא,
devarim she-be-farhesya, דברים שבצנעה. devarim she-be-tzina. Apparently that's the terminology that we're
getting around to, although we haven't exactly spelled that out. And again
the interesting thing that the private things, the language is being used
is רשות, reshut, which again the Rosh says means you have to
observe, but we just had an example by the shoes that it's
possible that somebody can choose to wear shoes, which makes it sound
like it really isn't an issue of רשות. reshut. Okay, let's take
a look. The גמרא Gemara continues. כל קרע שאינו בשעת חימום אינו
קרע.
Kol kera she-eino bi-sh'at
chimum eino kera.
So if it's a, the rending of the garment is not at
the time of being heated up, it's not a rending. I should
say that there's an important frame here. It's not that it's not
when the person is not emotional it doesn't count, because what are
we going to do, judge every person's internal state of emotional response?
So rather we're framing it in a more objective way, the time
of the emotional response. Meaning in the immediate aftermath of the death.
We can't police and determine what's going on for people internally, but
we can say the context in which it takes place.
Wait, is it death?
No, the קריעה kriyah happens after the death. So the גמרא Gemara
says... They go to the cemetery, right?
Some people wait till the cemetery, but the real act of קריעה
kriyah is at the time of the death.
Yeah. I mean I almost always see it done with like the
funeral home. Yeah. I mean, the primary time is בשעת יציאת נשמה.
bi-sh'at yetziat neshamah. I mean we have often postponed it, especially for
I don't know, a whole range of reasons. But anyway, but certainly
right after the burial still is שעת חימום, sh'at chimum, but the
primary time is at the time of the death. So the גמרא
Gemara says
like this. So the גמרא Gemara says okay. והא אמרו ליה לשמואל,
Ve-ha amru leh le-Shmuel, is that really true or did I skip
a line? Okay. כל קרע שאינו בשעת חימום אינו קרע. Kol kera
she-eino bi-sh'at chimum eino kera. והא אמרו ליה לשמואל נח נפשיה דרב,
Ve-ha amru leh le-Shmuel nach nafsheh de-Rav, where they told Shmuel that
Rav had passed away. קרע עליה תריסר מני Kara aleh treisar manei
and he rent twelve garments. אמר, Amar, he said, אזל גברא דהוה
מסתפינא מיניה, Azal gavra de-hava mistafina mineh, a man or the person
that I was afraid of has died. So normally you would think
why's that a bad thing? But it means as the רי"ף Rif
says, I was afraid of him because of all of his difficult
questions, you know? So it's meaning somebody that would really challenge me
and I really respected. Right. So אמרו ליה לרבי יוחנן, Amru leh
le-Rabbi Yochanan, they said to Rabbi Yochanan, נח נפשיה דרבי חנינא, Nach
nafsheh de-Rabbi Chanina, Rabbi Chanina passed away. קרע עליה תליסר איצטרי מילתא,
Kara aleh tlissar itztri milta, he rent thirteen, not twelve, thirteen
cloaks of like of silk. אמר אזל גברא דהוה מסתפינא מיניה, Amar
azal gavra de-hava mistafina mineh, somebody of whom I was, you know,
afraid of, somebody who really was a, you know, I was in
awe. So so you see that they were rending their garments and
I don't know how the גמרא Gemara knows it wasn't בשעת חימום.
bi-sh'at chimum. The גמרא Gemara somehow assumes that if it's not in
the immediate aftermath of the death or of the burial, it's not
considered שעת חימום, sh'at chimum, even though for this person subjectively they
may be first hearing about it now, so there for them maybe
it is. But again we're trying to deal with more an objective
definition of the context and the time and presumably that needs to
be in the immediate aftermath of the death. So therefore the גמרא
Gemara says, "Ah you see that it wasn't שעת חימום sh'at chimum
and they still did it?" So it says שאני רבנן דכיון דכל
שעתא מדכרי שמעתתא, Shani rabbanan de-keivan de-chol sha'ata midkri shma'teta, no, rabbis
are different because every moment they're thinking about their Torah and if
they're thinking about their Torah, they're thinking about the loss of this
colleague of theirs who would always be challenging them when they were
learning these things. וכשעת חימום דמי, U-ke-sh'at chimum dami, so it's like
the time of being like of heated up and emotional. Like it's
they're feeling it in a very immediate sense. And that does now
lose some of that objective measure and creates as they say a
very subjective standard. So if you take a look by the way
at תוספות, Tosafot, he says something here at the end of the
כל קרע. Kol kera. תוספות Tosafot says like
this. ולי נראה, Ve-li nireh, it's about halfway down line starting with
ולי. ve-li. ולי נראה דבכל שעה שיוכל להתחמם על מתו אפילו זמן
מרובה אחר מיתתו קרי שפיר בשעת חימום. Ve-li nireh de-ve-chol sha'ah she-yuchal
le-hitchamem al meto afilu zman merubeh achar mitato karei shapir bi-sh'at chimum.
Anytime that a person can really get worked up over it. Meaning
it's basically completely subjective standard, even if a long time after the
death would be שעת חימום. sh'at chimum. כמו שאמרו ברבנן משום דמדכרי
שמעתתא. Kmo she-amru be-rabbanan mishum de-midkri shma'teta. הוא הדין נמי בכל מאי
דיוכל להתחמם עליו. Hu ha-din nami be-chol mai de-yuchal le-hitchamem alav. Okay.
So he says yeah really this can be a very subjective standard.
It's possible to do קריעה kriyah much later if there's a subjective
reality that is present that means it sees it as a type
of an emotional response.
Probably not ideal. Right. Is it wrong then to do קריעה kriyah
at the wrong time?
Well, it doesn't count, a person isn't יוצא. yotzei. I mean. So
I guess you could sort of say, but if it's too late
to be יוצא *yotze*, so you could talk about, right, so you
could talk about so first, right, so it would mean that there's
no חיוב *chiyuv* to do it, to then start discussing whether it
would also be בל תשחית *bal tashchis*.
Right, right exactly. So yeah I mean is there anything wrong? You're
right. I mean if it's too late, it's too late. Certainly the
lesson from that would be not to postpone it until that time.
But but you're right at the bottom line so okay but did
they do something wrong? No there just wasn't a חיוב *chiyuv*. You
know most would say it was בל תשחית *bal tashchis*. All right
so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. אמר ליה Amar lei,
רבין בר אדא לרבא *Amar lei Rabin bar Adda leRava*. So Rabin
bar Adda says to Rava, אמר תלמידך רב Rav, עמרם *amar talmidcha
Rav Amram*. So your students Rav Amram said תניא *tanya* we taught
in the ברייתא *Baraisa*. אבל avel כל שבעה shiva קורעו לפניו *Avel
kol shiva korao lefanav*. The אבל aveil, *avel* the entire week the
rent of the garment is in front of him like visible. ואם
בא להחליף מחליף וקורע *Ve'im ba lehachalif machalif vekorea*. If he wants
to switch his garments,
he has to switch his garments and rend them again. בשבת b'Shabbos?
קורעו לאחוריו *BeShabbos korao leachorav*. Again you can't have public demonstration, so
the rent is behind the person, turns his garment around. ואם בא
להחליף מחליף ואינו קורע *Ve'im ba lehachalif machalif ve'eino korea*. So if
he wants to switch his garment he switches and obviously he doesn't
rend his garment it's שבת Shabbos. *Shabbos*. So on שבת Shabbos. *Shabbos*
you don't have to wear rent garment?
It says he can't, he doesn't have to.
No, he does. Yeah yeah so you don't wear yeah so you
don't wear rent garments on שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos*.
We thought it means he has to switch.
No, because what you could just turn it around and have it
not visible that way. One way or another way you don't have
it visible. Okay. But anyway, so שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* we already said
that you don't wear rent garments. But now we have this idea
that if you switch garments during the week you do קריעה *kriya*
again but that's not בשעת חימום *besha'as chimom* right? That's not immediately
in the aftermath. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, כי תניא ההיא
בכבוד אביו ואמו *ki tanya hahi bichvod aviv ve'imo*. No, that's only
you're right, but that's only about parents. For parents the idea of
having a rent garment on all the time and therefore rending it
afterwards
would be even if and here's a conceptual difference between the act
of קריעה *kriya* and the wearing of rent garments. Okay so the
act of קריעה *kriya* is no longer meaningful at this later time.
But for one's parents to always be wearing rent garments is important
as an act of כבוד אביו ואמו *kvod aviv ve'imo* and therefore
there has to be another rending of the garment if somebody changes
them during the week. Okay so in terms of the obligation of
קריעה *kriya* it's not meaningful after in the if it's not in
the immediate aftermath in term in terms of normal type of practices
it's not meaningful. But for כבוד אביו ואמו *kvod aviv ve'imo* it's
necessary it is necessary and meaningful. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* continues and by the way that's actually the הלכה halacha *halacha*
interestingly. Which is that if somebody switches their garment during the week
they don't have to do another קריעה *kriya*.
You know nevertheless of course you know most people choose to make
sure that they're you know at least when there are the מנחמים
*menachamim* over that they're wearing the garment that they did קריעה *kriya*
on as a real sign of the אבילות aveilus *aveilus* right? But
if somebody is you know if somebody is I don't know the
everybody has gone home and the person is took a shower and
is putting on you know some type of a you know some
type of a I don't know like you know of a shirt
you don't he doesn't do another קריעה *kriya* on it during the
שבעה shiva *shiva* if it's not אביו ואמו *aviv ve'imo*. Okay. So
now the גמרא *Gemara* says like this: אותן קרעים מתאחין או אין
מתאחין *oson krayim mis'achin o ein mis'achin*? These extra rendings which are
done not בשעת חימום *besha'as chimom* and are done for כבוד אביו
ואמו *kvod aviv ve'imo*, how much do they have a full status
of a torn garment? Can they be sewn up afterwards? Since it
was not בשעת חימום *besha'as chimom* it was just for כבוד אביו
ואמו *kvod aviv ve'imo*. So פליגי בה אבוה דרבי אושעיא ובר קפרא
*pligi bah avuha d'Rabbi Oshaya uBar Kappara*. So that's a debate. חד
אמר אין מתאחין *chad amar ein mis'achin*, you cannot sew them up
even though it wasn't בשעת חימום *besha'as chimom* if it was a
necessary for כבוד אביו ואמו *kvod aviv ve'imo* they don't get sewn
up. וחד אמר מתאחין *vechad amar mis'achin*, they can be sewn up.
תסתיים דאבוה דרבי אושעיא דאמר d'amar, אין מתאחין *tistayem d'avuha d'Rabbi Oshaya
d'amar ein mis'achin*. Let us conclude that the father of Rabbi Oshaya
would be the one that says they don't get sewn up. דאמר
רבי אושעיא *de'amar Rabbi Oshaya*, because Rabbi Oshaya his son said אין
מתאחין *ein mis'achin*, they don't get sewn up. So ממאן שמיע ליה
*miman shemiah lei*? Where else did he hear this idea that you
don't sew them up? לאו מאבוה *lav me'avuha*? Shouldn't it have been
from the father? לא *lo*, not necessarily, מבר קפרא רביה *miBar Kappara
rabeih*. Because his father the one that his father was arguing on
Bar Kappara was Rabbi Oshaya's רבי *rebbi*. So where did he get
it from? His רבי *rebbi* or his father? We don't know.
שמיע ליה *shmia lei*. Okay, anyway, well so we have this interesting
idea therefore about the act of קריעה *kriya* בשעת חימום *besha'as chimom*
distinguished from wearing rent garments which can be rent even when they
weren't בשעת חימום *besha'as chimom* but that's only an obligation of כבוד
אביו ואמו *kvod aviv ve'imo*, not an obligation of other אבילים *aveilim*.
And therefore
and again this interesting thing of is this an objective or subjective
standard of שעת חימום *sha'as chimom*. But back to our issue about
דברים שבצנעא dvarim she'be'tzina *devarim shebetzina* on שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos*. We have
the following wrap-up discussion.
Okay, אמר רבא *amar Rava*: אבל aveil, מטייל באונקלי בתוך ביתו *avel
metayel be'unkali betoch beiso*. An אבל aveil, *avel* can go walking around
with a type of a garment in his house. So what? But
the context means a rent garment. Okay, he can wear this rent
garment in his house and presumably also the context means on שבת
*Shabbos*. Okay, now that's a question. Why is that דברים שבצנעא dvarim
she'be'tzina? *devarim shebetzina*? So it seems to be being said here is
that דברים שבצנעא dvarim she'be'tzina *devarim shebetzina* in this context... So it
gets to Michael's point is also where are they being practiced. Right?
What do you mean בתוך ביתו? Of course, we just said a
while ago that an אבל aveil doesn't leave his house. But presumably
it means when he's in private. So now becomes an interesting question.
Practices that are very demonstrative, right, but nobody else is around. Okay,
and that seems to be what's being said here. Let's take a
look. אביי Abaye and again, you'll say I read all that context
in, none of that was there. But let's look at the next
story. אביי אשכחיה לרב יוסף Abaye ashchichei l'Rav Yosef Abaye found Rav
Yosef his rebbe, דפריס ליה סודרא ארישיה ואזל ואתי בביתיה. d'paris lei
sudara areishei v'azar v'asi beveitei. He was wearing a
like a scarf on his head, meaning he was doing a veiling,
and he was going around in his house. Okay, but for again,
presumably as we'll see in a minute, it was שבת. אמר ליה,
amar lei, he said to him, לאו סבר ליה מר אין אבילות
בשבת? lav savar lemar ein aveilus b'Shabbos? Don't you hold that there's
no אבילות aveilus. בשבת? And apparently it was a type of a
veiling which would have been going back to the earlier discussion, presumably
a type of דברים שבפרהסיא. dvarim she'be'farhesia. Made it very obvious it
was the sign of an אבילות. aveilus. Take it out. So why
are you doing this? It's a public observance of אבילות. aveilus So
אמר ליה, הכי אמר רבי יוחנן דברים שבצנעא נוהג. hachi amar Rabbi
Yochanan dvarim she'be'tzina noheg. No, it's private. Now, what did he mean
that it was private? Did he mean I'm doing it in private,
I'm doing it in my home? Or did he mean like we
said before, I don't consider this type of a veiling to be
public, this type of a veiling maybe is not so, it's not
עטיפת ישמעאלים, atipas Yishme'elim, right? So what? Okay, you know, whatever, it's
one of those things that was like the practice that's דברים שבצנעא
dvarim she'be'tzina you are obligated or at least allowed to do. Okay,
so it's not exactly clear. The conclusion seems to be clear that
the theme seems to be דברים שבצנעא נוהג. dvarim she'be'tzina noheg. What's
not clear is number one this concept of רשות reshus because notice
by the way even in this last story it says he saw
him doing it. There's never a sense like he had to be
doing it although the language of דברים שבצנעא נוהג dvarim she'be'tzina noheg
and this is where the ראש Rosh is coming from. נוהג noheg
sounds like our practice, not like this discretion, they have to be
practiced. Okay, so on the one hand we have this issue of
is there a discretion or not. Again, we've discussed that. The end,
the language of נוהג noheg sounds like you have to. But the
other big question is what is דברים שבצנעא? dvarim she'be'tzina Is the
reason this was דברים שבצנעא dvarim she'be'tzina? because it was private and
therefore all practices you have to do if nobody else is around?
Or is this דברים שבצנעא dvarim she'be'tzina, because it's not such a
demonstrative act of אבילות aveilus like we said before. So if you
take a look at תוספות, Tosfos, תוספות הכי אמר רבי יוחנן Tosfos
hachi amar Rabbi Yochanan says,
okay,
it says like this. מספקא
ליה,
Mesapka lei,
the last narrow lines of תוספות, Tosfos, right, right where it says
you see the last lines with אמרין. amrin. מספקא ליה, Mesapka lei,
I have a doubt כי היכא דשרי בתוך ביתו, ki heicha de'shari
betoch beiso, again notice the word we allow, again allow or obligate.
Allow privately in one's house הני דברים דקריעה hani dvarim de'kria like
the rent garment or the wrapped head. אי הוי אסור נעילת הסנדל
בצנעא וכל שאר דברים. Ee havi asur ne'ilas hasandal betzina v'chol shaar
dvarim. Maybe now all practices of אבילות aveilus have to be done
in private. So is דברים שבצנעא Devarim she-be-tzina, mean where they're done
or the types of practices that are being done? We basically ruled
that it doesn't matter where it's done and if people are around.
It's basically the nature of the practice and the one exception is
the sex because that is fundamentally a very intimate and private act.
Take it away, if other people were knowing it would be clearly
public that you're, you know, whatever. But also not merely because the
non-having of sex doesn't mean anything. It's the having of sex that
shows something. The non-having of sex is that a סימן siman of
אבילות aveilus or not? So all these things we say that you
know it's basically the character of the act and how much its
observing it makes a statement of אבילות aveilus or not and not
the question of whether it takes place in private or public although
in the end the last story might make us question that and
תוספות Tosfos leaves with a question mark about that. So maybe certain
practices if nobody are around you're allowed to do or maybe you're
obligated to do.
What would it be? It would just be the sex and maybe
the washing of the face.
What do you mean? All the practices, you know, having a rent
garment on, not wearing shoes.
No, but what you would be allowed to do to turn the
אבילות aveilus? would only be I
mean I mean the sex and the washing of your face you
couldn't do on שבת. Everything else would be בפרהסיא, be'farhesia, right?
No, תוספות' Tosfos' question is if nobody else is around.
Right, no, I'm saying the other side of it would be that
if it's just a thing that's fundamentally private or public, the only
thing that would
be, what are you asking? What constitutes דברים שבצנעא? Devarim she-be-tzina. Yeah.
So in the end of the day what constitutes דברים שבצנעא, devarim
she-be-tzina. right the גמרא basically has mentioned
the sex, the wearing of the shoes and the bathing. Now wearing
of the shoes changed over time. So if you take a look
in the שלחן ערוך, Shulchan Aruch, right, the about what actually constitutes
it nowadays, I'll just read you very quickly,
let me just find it
here,
here he says like this, he says.
דברים שבצנעא, devarim she-be-tzina תשמיש המיטה Tashmish Ha-mita ורחיצה. v'rechitza. Okay? And
then that's all the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch lists as דברים שבצנעא.
And then he says wearing shoes is considered
פרהסיא parhesia nowadays, etc., etc. And then he has a question that
תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah הוי דברים שבצנעא. havei devarim she-be-tzina. So not
learning תורה, Torah, that might be considered דברים שבצנעא. A person's not
learning תורה, Torah, is it obvious he's doing it because of אבילות?
aveilus, There's other reasons maybe the person isn't learning תורה. Torah. And
then, and this is all from the רא"ש, Rosh, but I just
wanted to read this because it's interesting, אבל לעצור הפרשה, aval la'atzor
haparsha, כיוון שחייב אדם להשלים פרשיותיו עם הציבור keivan she'chayiv adam l'hashlim
parshiyosav im hatzibbur הוי כקריאת שמע ומותר. havei ki'krias shema u'muttar. Okay,
that's just like davening when you're doing מעביר סדרה, maavir sedra, which
by the way could be an argument to do it even not
on שבת, could be an argument to do it the rest of
the week, it's just like I'm מחזיר machzir the פרשה, parsha, let's
say you learn it, do an עליה aliyah each day.
But anyway, ואם קראת אדם, v'im karata adam, here's a story about
רבינו תם. Rabbeinu Tam. ואם קראת אדם לעלות לתורה, v'im karata adam
la'alos l'Torah, צריך לעלות, tzarich la'alos, שאימה יהיה נמנע she'im haya nimna
הרי הוא
דבר של פרהסיא. harei hu davar shel parhesia. Maybe don't give him
an עליה, aliyah, but if you gave him an עליה, aliyah, he
can't then not go up and say no, I can't come up
because I'm an אבל, because then it's making a public announcement.
Okay. ורבינו תם, v'Rabbeinu Tam, here's the story, this is from the
רא"ש, Rosh, היו קוראים אותו בכל פעם שלישי. hayu korim oso bechol
pa'am shlishi. Every single שבת he would get שלישי. shlishi. וארע בו
אבילות, v'ira bo aveilus, once he was an
אבל, ולא קראו החזן, v'lo kara'o hachazzan, and he just went up
on his
own! ועלה הוא מעצמו. v'ala hu me'atzmo. It's שלישי, shlishi, it's my
עליה! aliyah! דאמר, כיוון שהורגל לקרותו שלישי בכל שבת, keivan she'hurga likroso
shlishi bechol Shabbos, הרי שאינו עולה, harei she'eino oleh, if I wouldn't
be getting up right now for the עליה aliyah whether you called
me or not, אומר שבשביל אבילות הוא נמנע, omeir shebishvil aveilus hu
nimna, everybody would say oh, רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam isn't getting an
עליה aliyah because he's an אבל, והוי דברים שבפרהסיא. v'havei devarim she'be-parhesia.
Okay. So basically at the end of the day, other than that
fascinating story with רבינו תם, Rabbeinu Tam, the really only דברים שבצנעא
we're left with is the sex and the bathing.
But he says it's cool.
Yeah. All right. Now so now we move on. Again, and this
whole idea of רשות reshus and of practices in the house where
nobody else is looking doesn't have any echo and really just left
and the shoes becomes different because of changed circumstances. So we're really
just left with two practices.
Moving on. רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, משחרב בית המקדש mi'shecharav
Beis HaMikdash עצרת כשבת. Atzeres k'Shabbos. Going back to the משנה. Mishnah.
What counts as a רגל? reghel? So רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says
once there was no longer בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, שבועות Shavuos counts
only like שבת, it could be because there's no seven day aspect
of שבועות Shavuos because there's no תשלומין, tashlumin, although why you need
seven days isn't clear, I would say more because the primary observance
of שבועות, Shavuos, what makes שבועות Shavuos a distinct, what gives it
its weight is the observance in the מקדש, Mikdash, there's very little
in terms of its ritual other than not doing מלאכה melacha outside
of the מקדש. Mikdash. But anyway, that's his position, which then and
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel disagrees in the משנה. Mishnah. אמר רב גידל
בר מנשיא אמר שמואל אמר רבן גמליאל. Amar Rav Gidal bar Menashia
amar Shmuel amar Rabban Gamliel. הלכה כרבן גמליאל. Halacha k'Rabban Gamliel.
We rule like רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel that עצרת Atzeres counts as
a full רגל reghel and it's מפסיק mafsik the אבילות, aveilus, and
not only that, that ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and יום כיפור Yom
Kippur count as a רגל reghel and are מפסיק mafsik the אבילות,
aveilus even though those you would say don't have the same quality
of שמחה. simcha. Okay? So we פסקן pasken that way. So now
he says like this: איכא דמתני לה אהא דרב גידל בר מנשיא
הא, ika d'masni lah aha d'Rav Gidal bar Menashia ha, some teach
that idea that we rule like רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel not on
this הלכה halacha of אבילות aveilus. about שבועות Shavuos and ראש השנה
Rosh Hashanah and יום כיפור Yom Kippur all having the weight of
a רגל, reghel, but on the following הלכה halacha of אבילות. aveilus
כל שלושים יום, kol sheloshim yom, if an infant dies within
thirty days, תינוק יוצא בחיק, tinok yotzei be'cheik, he's not brought out
in a coffin, he's just carried in the chest, like he's carried
against the body. ונקבר באשה אחת ושני אנשים, v'nikbar b'isha achas u'shnei
anashim, and the burial takes place with one woman and two men.
אבל לא באיש אחד ושתי נשים, aval lo b'ish echad u'shtei nashim,
not with one man and two women, which more has to do
with ייחוד yichud problems. Again, why we're describing how many people, presumably
the point is not in a major public type of a way,
which is a fascinating issue, because well we'll take a look, but
certainly within thirty days, as a general rule's considered to be a
נפל, nefel, which also raises whole questions about burial for נפלים nefalim
and אבילות aveilus for נפלים nefalim and so on. Let's read the
whole thing. אבא שאול אומר Abba Shaul omer what?
No, who's the אשה אחת? isha achas? It could be the mother,
okay. אבא שאול אומר אף באיש אחד ושתי נשים, Abba Shaul omer
af b'ish echad u'shtei nashim, even one man and two women, even
though there might be sometimes some ייחוד yichud problems with it, here
we're not concerned. ואין עומדים עליו בשורה, v'ein omdim alav b'shurah, there's
not this row of after the funeral of consoling the mourners. ואין
אומרים עליו ברכת אבלים ותנחומי אבלים, v'ein omrim alav birkas avelim v'tanchumei
avelim, and you don't say the whole formal blessings that are said
for the אבל and for the תנחומים, tanchumim, there are certain ברכות
brachos that we don't do those anymore nowadays, okay, and all of
this is because basically it's not it's still considered at this stage
to be
a miscarriage, I mean it's not a miscarriage but still considered that
the baby was not yet had what's called in הלכה halakha חזקת
חיים, chezkat chayim, especially in those days you understand that, and therefore
it's not treated as a normal אבילות would be treated.
But תוספות Tosafos has an interesting distinction about that. If you look
at תוספות Tosafos אינם עולים בברכת אבלים, einam ohleh b'birchas avelim, תוספות
Tosafos says פירש בקונטרס דמאי ולא כלו לחדשיו peirash b'kuntres d'mai v'lo
kuleh l'chadasha that it's a case where the months have not completed
meaning that maybe it was not born full term and therefore it's
not necessarily what we would have said as has proven that it's
viable yet. ומיהו אפילו מאי דכלו לחדשיו. u'mihu afilu mai d'kalu l'chadashav.
and תוספות Tosafos says, but I disagree. We should not we should
not assume that the same discussion about practicing שבעה shiva is what's
going on here. Here we're talking much more about the burial context
and not the שבעה shiva context. So it could be it was
a full-term baby and therefore even if he dies within the first
month חס ושלום, chas v'shalom, a full-term baby sit שבעה on because
if it's full-term it's considered to be
viable. נהי דמתאבלין עלויה כדפי' ר' אליעזר בפרק יש בכור, nehi d'mis'ablin
alav k'dif'reish Rabi Eliezer b'perek Yesh Bechor, even though there would be
אבלות, avelus, מכל מקום אין מחמירים עליו כל כך לצערו כדאשכחן בהני
דסמוך. mi'kol makom ein machmirim alav kol kach l'tza'aro k'dashkachan b'hanei d'samuch.
and I don't know what לצערו l'tza'aro means, like for his for
anguish over him. You you don't make so many like demands in
terms of some of these particularly burial practices. דלפי מה שהוא גדול
מחמירים לכבודו. d'lefi mah she'hu gadol machmirim l'khvodo. Interesting different phrases, לצערו
l'tza'aro and לכבודו. l'khvodo. But there's an interesting question here, look it's
an interesting question in time when cases of miscarriage and so on.
How do you properly commemorate the loss, but you know, but also,
you know, you know sort of I'm trying to say this in
a way that's properly sensitive, but you know, somewhat like keep it
in proportion, like you know, and and that sort of seems to
be what's going on here. Yes, it was baby was viable, you
sit שבעה and so on, but you know, still how much have
the parents really, you know, anyway, there's a there's a real grappling
here with striking the right balance of what it means, you know,
of how to do this in a way that doesn't skew things.
So let's keep let's read a little bit more. בין שלשים יום,
ben shloshim yom, once it's 30 days, יוצא בדלוסקמא, yotzeh b'dlusk'ma, is
brought out in some type of a of a mini coffin. רבי
יהודה אומר, Rabi Yehuda omer,
לא דלוסקמא
אלא ניטלת בכתף,
lo
dlusk'ma ela
nitelet b'katef, not such a small one that you could just put
it on a shoulder, one person's shoulder, אלא ניטלת באגפיים, ela nitelet
b'agapayim, has to be carried in the arms, and Rabbenu Gershom says
two people. ועומדים עליו בשורה, v'omdim alav b'shura, and you do have
the whole row of the of the consolers, ואומרים עליו ברכת אבלים
ותנחומי אבלים. v'omrim alav birchas avelim v'tanchumei avelim. Now בן י"ב חודש,
ben yud-bet chodesh, if it's already a year old, יוצא במיטה, yotzeh
b'mita, it's brought out in like a full
funeral bier with like a full-sized coffin. רבי עקיבא אומר, Rabi Akiva
omer, הוא בן שנה וכאילו בן שתים, hu ben shana v'ke'ilu ben
shtayim,
if he's a year old but he's as big as a two
year old, או בן שתים וכאילו בן שנה, o ben shtayim v'ke'ilu
ben shana, two year old even if he's as small as a
one year old, יוצא במיטה, yotzeh b'mita, then he would go out.
So it sounds like רבי עקיבא Rabi Akiva is being more strict,
only when he's older or looks older would he get the full
thing. תוספות Tosafos points out that in another version of this, the
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma said he had to be three years before
you do the full thing, and רבי עקיבא Rabi Akiva says even
if he's two years or looks like two years. רבי שמעון בן
אלעזר אומר, Rabi Shimon ben Elazar omer, היוצא במיטה, hayotzeh b'mita, when
it's this stage of יוצא במיטה yotzeh b'mita that we've been talking
about, one year or two years or three years, in that case,
רבים מתעצבים עליו. rabim mit'atzvim alav. The masters sort of gather for
him or whatever. So if Rabbenu Gershom says what מתעצבים mit'atzvim means,
he says מרגישים ומצערים, margishim u'mitza'arim, like there's a more communal participation
in the אבלות. avelus. רבי אלעזר בן עזריה אומר, Rabi Eliezer ben
Azaria omer, I'm sorry, וכל שאינו יוצא במיטה, v'chol she'eino yotzeh b'mita,
but earlier than that age of one or two or three years,
אין רבים מתעצבים עליו, ein rabim mit'atzvim alav, you do not get
everybody the whole community worked up over it. I mean again, it's
more of like of a private than of a public thing because
again, this was somebody that actually, you know, did not yet sort
of, you know, didn't make a mark in the community yet. So
it becomes a very like, you know, it's a very funny thing
about how to react to somebody who did not yet have like
a personality, you know, that was noticed noticed in the community. Obviously
although the parents are deeply suffering. רבי אלעזר בן עזריה אומר, Rabi
Eliezer ben Azaria omer, ניכר לרבים, nikar l'rabim, and he really sort
of gets to the point. Once somebody is known in the community,
רבים מתעסקין עמו, rabim mis'askin imo, then the community sort of gets
involved. Motivate? Yeah, right.
No, not like an adult.
But it means, you know, once somebody sees the kid around. Like
it doesn't mean somebody's a private hermit. That's not what we're talking
about there. We mean, you know, if the kid is he's still
totally, you know, at home and nobody sees him, it's one thing.
Once a kid starts running around in the street and whatever, and
parents start taking him out, you know, whatever, and people see him,
then... אינו ניכר לרבים, eino nikar l'rabim, when it's not yet noticed
by the community, אין רבים מתעסקין עמו. ein rabim mis'askin imo. ומה
הן בהספד? u'mah hen b'hesped? Now how about giving about a eulogy?
What's the story with that, right? And what do you say when
you eulogize somebody who's so young? רבי מאיר בשם רבי ישמעאל אומר,
Rabi Meir b'shem Rabi Yishmael omer, עניים בני שלש עשירים בני חמש.
aniyim b'nei shalosh ashirim b'nei chamesh. In so it's
the children of poor people you eulogize them three years old, of
rich people five. What's the difference? So so Rabbenu Gershom says that
if you look at him he says לפי שהעני מצטער בבניו יותר
מן העשיר לפי שאין לו שמחה אחרת, lefi she'he'ani mitzta'er b'banav yoser
min he'ashir lefi she'ein lo simcha acheres, which is quite fascinating. I
would have thought differently, that again this has to do more with
sort of the degree that the person is in the community and...
Poor people, you know, they can't afford home care as much, they
don't, you know, whatever, these rich people can keep their kids more
home and sheltered, poor people have less options. ר' יהודה אומר משמו
עני בני חמש עשיר בני שש. Rebbi Yehuda Omer Mishmo ani bnei
chamesh ashir bnei shesh. No, even for poor people, only at five
years old is there you do a הספד hesped which speaks about,
you know, the dead and, you know, about the and, you know,
what do you say when it's such a young child? ובני זקני
כבני עניים. Uvnei zekeini kivnei ani'im. And this sort of reflects רבינו
גרשום's Rabbeinu Gershom approach because it says, you know, children of older
people, older parents are like children of עניים. ani'im. Why? So presumably
the comparison here is because of, you know, it's sort of like
the whole idea of the בן זקונים, Ben Zekunim, like, you know,
people that finally in their old age had a child, the loss
presumably is that much more tragic. And in this context, אמר רב
גידל בר מנשיא אמר רב הלכה כרבי יהודה שאמר משום רבי ישמעאל.
Amar Rav Gidel bar Minyasha Amar Rav halakha k'Rebbi Yehuda she'amar mishum
Rebbi Yishmael. We say like רבי ישמעאל, Rebbi Yishmael, so and which
is this last teaching of what was it? Yeah, this last teaching
about בני עשירים ובני עניים. bnei ashirim u'vnei ani'im. So this was,
so when the גמרא said earlier, this is all into the earlier
statement when the גמרא said that אמר רב גידל בר מנשיא אמר
שמואל הלכה כרבן גמליאל, Amar Rav Gidel bar Minyasha Amar Shmuel halakha
k'Rabban Gamliel, that it was not about the status of the רגלים,
Regalim, but it was this status about about when there when one
does a הספד, hesped, although it's not the exact same thing because
this is this is the הלכה halakha is כרבי יהודה k'Rebbi Yehuda
and here it's the הלכה is כרבן גמליאל. k'Rabban Gamliel. But anyway,
it's another ruling that so when when רב גידל Rav Gidel said
in the name of רב, he made a certain ruling in הלכות
אבילות, Hilkhot Aveilut, it wasn't the ruling about the idea of the
רגלים, Regalim, it was this ruling in terms of issues around mourning
practices or maybe not mourning practices, community practices, ניחום אבלים, nichum aveilim,
הספד, hesped, burial practices around the death of small children.
That's where he was giving his פסק, psak, not in the רגלים.
Regalim. Okay, so we'll have to end here, we will finish tomorrow
with the actual פסק הלכה psak halakha relating to the רגלים. Regalim.